<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
    <header> 
        <title>Sámi proofing tools project</title>

	<authors>
	  <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
	</authors>

    </header> 
    <body> 
        <section>
          <title>What is Divvun?</title>
	  
	  <p>Divvun is a project run by the Sámi Parliament in order
	  to make spell checkers for the Sámi languages. In the first
	  phase of the project this means spell checkers and
	  hyphenation for Northern Sámi, and spell checkers for Lule
	  Sámi - the background for this prioritising is found on these pages (in <a href="sma-background.nb.html">Norwegian</a> or in
	  <a href="sma-background.se.html">Sámi</a>). The tools will work on Windows, Linux and Mac, with
	  the usual office environment programs.</p>

	   </section>
	   
	   <section>
	       <title>Background</title>
	       
	       <p>The project was planned and thereafter started
	       because the Sámi Parliament wanted to give Sámi
	       speakers and other Sámi users the same writing aid
	       tools as Norwegian speakers. This is especially
	       important because many Sámi speakers never learned to
	       write Sámi in school. The project is part of a larger
	       policy to strengthen the Sámi languages, and to
	       increase the use of Sámi as a written language.</p>
	       
	   <p> The project is financed by <em>The Sámi
	   Parliament</em>, og <em>Kommunal- og
	   regionaldepartementet</em>, <em>Undervisnings- og
	   forskningsdepartementet</em> and <em>Kultur- og
	   kirkedepartementet</em> (TODO: names in English), and the
	   final programs will be accessible for all wanting to write
	   in Sámi.</p>
           
           <p>We aim at making spell checkers that are geared towards
           Sámi as it is used both in Norway, Sweden and
           Finland. Since the project is run as a Norwegian project
           only, the final programs may have a Norwegian bias. If this
           will be the case, it is against our intentions, we want
           programs that may be used by all users, irrespective of
           country of origin.</p>
           </section>
           
           <section>
            <title>Organising</title>
            
            <p>The project is run by the language department of the
            Sámi Parliament. It has its own board, with members from
            the Sámi Parliament, the Ministries, and the University of
            Tromsø. The work is conducted by a group of five
            members:</p>
            
            
        <ul>
          <li>Børre Gaup (project worker, borre punkt gaup at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Sjur N. Moshagen (project leader, sjur punkt moshagen at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Thomas Omma (linguist, thomas punkt omma at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Maaren Palismaa (linguist, maren punkt palismaa at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Tomi Pieski (programmer, tomi punkt pieski at samediggi punkt no)</li>
        </ul>

        <p>The project is based upon work done at the University of
        Tromsø, and has a close and daily cooperation with the
        language technology group there, so close that most of our
        infrastructure is shared (cf. the tab "<a
        href="http://giellatekno.uit.no">Samisk disamb.</a>"
        above).</p>



        <p>At project kickoff, the detailed list of deliberable programs looked as follows:</p>

        <table>
          <caption>Overview over planned products</caption>
          <tr><th>Program/OS</th>      <th>Spell checker</th><th>Hyphenation</th></tr>
          <tr><td>MS Office/Win</td>   <td>x</td>            <td>x</td>        </tr>
          <tr><td>MS Office/Mac</td>   <td>x</td>            <td>x</td>        </tr>
          <tr><td>OpenOffice/Win</td>  <td>x</td>            <td>?</td>        </tr>
          <tr><td>OpenOffice/Mac</td>  <td>x</td>            <td>?</td>        </tr>
          <tr><td>OpenOffice/Linux</td><td>x</td>            <td>?</td>        </tr>
          <tr><td>InDesign CS</td>     <td>-</td>            <td>x</td>        </tr>
          <tr><td>Aspell (Win/Mac/Linux)</td><td>x</td>      <td></td>        </tr>
        </table>

        <p>This list may be adjusted during the course of the project, but there will probably not undergo substantial revisions.</p>

        <p>The project will offer early test versions (so called alpha- and betaversions) for interested users (betatesters). When the firest test version is made accessible, we will publish more information on testing and usage. A more detailed project plan, with important milestones for the different projects may be found <a href="timetable.html">here</a>, and some more details on how the work is being conducted may be found <a href="howmake.html">here</a>.
           See also the final section, containing useful links.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The language policy of the projectet</title>

        <p>The project is multilingual, and this will be true also for our written documentation, cf. <a href="lang-policy.en.html">The language policy of the projectet</a>.</p>

        <p>The project does not have its own policy for the standardisation of the Sámi written languages, and it will follow all decisions made by Sámi language bodies. When the decided norm is unclear, we will ask for a clarification from these bodies.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Useful links</title>

        <ul>
          <li><a href="">RSS news from the project</a></li>
          <li><a href="mailto:divvun ved samediggi punkt no">E-mail to the project</a></li>
          <li><a href="">Aspell</a></li>
          <li><a href="">OpenOffice</a></li>
          <li><a href="">Xerox FST-tools</a></li>
          <li><a href="">E-mail to the project</a></li>
          <li><a href="">...</a></li>
        </ul>

      </section>	  
	    <p>Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>


    </body>
</document>
