<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en"> 
  <header> 
    <title>Divvun - Sámi proofing tools project</title>
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Version 1.0 available!</title>
      <p>
		New beta 2 versions of the spellers for Sámi are available for download. As of May 29, the first public release of the Sámi proofing tools is available. This is an historic event in the Sámi computing age, and marks an important milestone in keeping Sámi alive in the modern society. The tools are available here:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
        	<a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/DivvunInstaller.exe">Windows</a>
        </li>
        <li>
        	<a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/sami-proofing-tools.dmg">MacOS X</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
		More information and details on the new versions are found in the <a href="doc/proof/spelling/msoff/install_use.html">release notes</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>What is Divvun?</title>
      <p>
		Divvun is a project run by the Sámi Parliament in order to make spell checkers for the Sámi languages. In the first phase of the project this means spell checkers and hyphenation for Northern and Lule Sámi. The tools work on Windows, Linux and Mac, with the usual office environment programs.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Finished products</title>
        <p>
		  The final proofing tools are available free of charge by downloading from the project home page. The downloads are traditional installers that install the proofing tools easily on the users' computers. The proofing tools work the same way as proofing tools for other languages. The Norwegian Sámi Parliament and the University of Tromsø retain the rights to most of the produced software, together with the copyright holders of whatever is included. All interested parties can both use the software and download the source code free of charge (only our source code).
        </p>
      <table>
        <caption>Overview over available and planned products</caption>
        <tr>
          <th>Program/OS</th>
          <th>Spell checker</th>
          <th>Hyphenation</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>MS Office/Win</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://www.divvun.no/DivvunInstaller.exe">Official version 1.0 is available</a>
          </td>
          <td>Is installed together with the spell checker</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>MS Office/Mac</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/sami-proofing-tools.dmg">Official version 1.0 is available</a>
          </td>
          <td>with the spell checker</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>InDesign CS3</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>OpenOffice/Win</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>OpenOffice/Mac</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>OpenOffice/Linux</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
      </table>
      <p>
        This list may be adjusted during the course of the project, but there
        will probably not undergo substantial revisions.
      </p>
    <section>
        <title>Source code and documentation</title>
        <section>
            <title>Anonymous cvs</title>
            <p>
                The source code to this project is open source, and it is available through <a href="doc/infra/anonymous-cvs.html">anonymous cvs</a>. We have also written a document on how to <a href="doc/intro.html">find your way</a> through the source code.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Download documentation</title>
            <p>
                All the documentation on this project is available on this site. If you would like to have this documentation on your own computer, follow the instruction on <a href="doc/infra/anonymous-cvs.html">anonymous cvs</a>, then go on to  <a href="doc/infra/forrest-howto.html">setup forrest</a>. After that all our documentation sits on your own computer, and you can navigate through it with a web browser.
             </p>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Useful links</title>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="mailto:divvun at samediggi dot no">E-mail to the
          project</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://hunspell.sourceforge.net/">Hunspell</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice.org</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
          href="http://www.xrce.xerox.com/competencies/content-analysis/fst/">
          Xerox FST-tools</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <p class="last_modified">
        Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$
    </p>
  </body>
</document>
