<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
    <header> 
        <title>Sámi proofing tools project</title>

	<authors>
	  <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
	</authors>

    </header> 
    <body> 
        <section>
          <title>What is Divvun?</title>
	  
	  <p>Divvun is a project run by the Sámi Parliament in order to make spell checkers for the Sámi languages. In the first phase of the project this means spell checkers and hyphenation for Northern Sámi, and spell checkers for Lule Sámi - the background for this prioritising is found  <a href="sma-background.html">here</a> (in Norwegian or in Sámi). The tools will work on Windows, Linux and Mac, with the usual office environment programs.</p>
	   </section>
	   
	   <section>
	       <title>Background</title>
	       
	       <p>The project was planned and thereafter started because the Sámi Parliament wanted to give Sámi speakers and other Sámi users the same writing aid tools as Norwegian speakers. This is especially important because many Sámi speakers never learned to write Sámi in school. The project is part of a larger policy to strengthen the Sámi languages, and to increase the use of Sámi as a written language.</p>
	       
	       The project is financed by <em>The Sámi Parliament</em>, og <em>Kommunal- og
           regionaldepartementet</em>, <em>Undervisnings- og forskningsdepartementet</em>
           and <em>Kultur- og kirkedepartementet</em> (TODO: names in English), and the final programs will be accessible for all wanting to write in Sámi.</p>
           
           <p>We aim at making spell checkers that are geared towards Sámi as it is used both in Norway, Sweden and Finland. Since the project is run as a Norwegian project only, the final programs may have a Norwegian bias. If this will be the case, it is against our intentions, we want programs that may be used by all users, irrespective of country of origin.</p>
           </section>
           
           <section>
            <title>Organising</title>
            
            <p>The project is run by the language department of the Sámi Parliament. It has its own board, with members from the Sámi Parliament, the Ministries, and the University of Tromsø. The work is conducted by a group of five members:</p>
            
            
        <ul>
          <li>Børre Gaup (project worker, borre punkt gaup at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Sjur N. Moshagen (project leader, sjur punkt moshagen at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Thomas Omma (linguist, thomas punkt omma at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Maaren Palismaa (linguist, maren punkt palismaa at samediggi punkt no)</li>
          <li>Tomi Pieski (programmer, tomi punkt pieski at samediggi punkt no)</li>
        </ul>

        <p>The project is based upon work done at the University of  Tromsø, and has a close and daily cooperation with the language technology group there, so close that most of our infrastructure is shared (cf. the tab  "<a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no">Samisk
           disamb.</a>" above).</p>
      </section>       

	  
	    <p>Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
