<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en"> 
  <header> 
    <title>Divvun - Sámi proofing tools project</title>
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Public Beta available!</title>
      <p>
        As of May 29, the first public release of the Sámi proofing tools is
        available. This is an historic event in the Sámi computing age, and
        marks an important milestone in keeping Sámi alive in the modern
        society. Go directly to our <a href="downloads.html">download page</a>,
        or read more about the release in the <a
        href="doc/proof/spelling/msoff/install_use.en.html">release notes</a>,
        or download here:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/sami-proofing-tools-20070529.zip">Win</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/sami-proofing-tools-20070529.dmg">Mac</a></li>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>What is Divvun?</title>
      <p>
        Divvun is a project run by the Sámi Parliament in order to make spell
        checkers for the Sámi languages. In the first phase of the project this
        means spell checkers and hyphenation for Northern Sámi, and spell
        checkers for Lule Sámi - the background for this prioritising is found
         <a href="sma-background.html">on this page</a>. The tools will work on
        Windows, Linux and Mac, with the usual office environment programs.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Finished products</title>
        <p>
          When the project is closing at the end of 2007, the final proofing
          tools will be available free of charge by downloading from the project
          home page. The downloads are traditional installers that install the
          the proofing tools easily on the users' computers. The proofing tools
          work the same way as proofing tools for other languages. The Norwegian
          Sámi Parliament and the University of Tromsø retain the rights to most
          of the produced software, together with the copyright holders of
          whatever is included. All interested parties can both use the software
          and download the source code free of charge (only our source code).
        </p>
      <p>
        At project kickoff, the detailed list of deliverable programs looked as
        follows:
      </p>
      <table>
        <caption>Overview over planned products</caption>
        <tr>
          <th>Program/OS</th>
          <th>Spell checker</th>
          <th>Hyphenation</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>MS Office/Win</td>
          <td><a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/sami-proofing-tools-20070529.zip">Beta available</a></td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>MS Office/Mac</td>
          <td><a href="http://www.divvun.no/static_files/sami-proofing-tools-20070529.dmg">Beta available</a></td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>OpenOffice/Win</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td>?</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr><td>OpenOffice/Mac</td>  <td>x</td>            <td>?</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>OpenOffice/Linux</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td>?</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>InDesign CS</td>
          <td>-</td>
          <td>x</td>       
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Aspell (Win/Mac/Linux)</td>
          <td>x</td>
          <td></td>       
        </tr>
      </table>
      <p>
        This list may be adjusted during the course of the project, but there
        will probably not undergo substantial revisions.
      </p>
      <p>
        The project will offer early test versions (so called alpha- and
        betaversions) for interested users (betatesters). When the firest test
        version is made accessible, we will publish more information on testing
        and usage. A more detailed project plan, with important milestones for
        the different projects may be found <a
        href="timetable.html">here</a>, and some more details on how the work
        is being conducted may be found <a href="howmake.html">here</a>.
        See also the final section, containing useful links.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Source code and documentation</title>
        <section>
            <title>Anonymous cvs</title>
            <p>
                The source code to this project is open source, and it is available
                through <a href="doc/infra/anonymous-cvs.html">anonymous cvs</a>. We have also written 
                a document on how to <a href="doc/intro.html">find your way</a> through the
                source code.
            </p>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Download documentation</title>
            <p>
                All the documentation on this project is available on this
                site. If you would like to have this documentation on your
                own computer, follow the instruction on 
                <a href="doc/infra/anonymous-cvs.html">anonymous cvs</a>, then go on to 
                <a href="doc/infra/forrest-howto.html">setup forrest</a>. 
                After that all our documentation sits on your own computer, and 
                you can navigate through it with a web browser.
             </p>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Useful links</title>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="mailto:divvun at samediggi dot no">E-mail to the
          project</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://aspell.sourceforge.net/">Aspell</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
          href="http://www.xrce.xerox.com/competencies/content-analysis/fst/">
          Xerox FST-tools</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <p class="last_modified">
        Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$
    </p>
  </body>
</document>
