<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing — Overview</title>

    <subtitle>Overview of all documents relating to outsourcing</subtitle>

    <version>0.1</version>

    <type>Internal draft</type>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjurnm@mac.com" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>

    <abstract>Integration of proofing tools with commercial applications like
    Adobe InDesign and Microsoft Office is very time consuming and errouneous
    without experience and former practice. It has thus been decided as the
    most cost-effective solution to outsource these tasks. — This document
    gives an overview of all documents relating to the outsourcing.</abstract>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Background information</title>

      <p>Below is a list of documents, information and templates useful for
      outsourcing through an open competition (public tender) within the rules
      of EEC/EU.</p>

      <ul>
        <li><a
        href="http://www.odin.dep.no/nhd/norsk/publ/veiledninger/024081-120012/index-dok000-b-n-a.html">Guide
        to regulations on public investments</a> (the title is a free
        translation, the original title as well as the whole document are in
        Norwegian)</li>

        <li><a
        href="http://odin.dep.no/nhd/norsk/dok/andre_dok/veiledninger/024081-120012/hov015-nn.html">Contact
        points</a> for questions relating to public tenders (in
        Norwegian)</li>

        <li><a
        href="http://odin.dep.no/nhd/norsk/dok/andre_dok/veiledninger/024081-120019/dok-nn.html">Best
        practises</a> - a guide to public tenders (in Norwegian)</li>

        <li><a
        href="http://odin.dep.no/filarkiv/205310/vedlegg1.doc">Template</a>
        for Public Tender Document (MS Word document)</li>

        <li>Deadlines for public tenders</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Competition Process</title>

      <p>The round of public tender (the competition) is held according to
      rules by the Norwegian government, and is in accordance with EU/EEC
      regulations. The following is the planned schedule and process (the
      dates may still shift):</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Selection criterion, the exact list of deliveries and the schedule
        will be decided by the project board at their meeting October
        4<sup>th</sup></li>

        <li>The public tender will be opened about two months after the
        project board meeting (suggestion: November 20<sup>th</sup>)</li>

        <li>Attending companies should deliver their offer within the
        deadline, which is minimum 52 days after the public tender has been
        opened (if opened at November 20<sup>th</sup>, the deadline would be
        at earliest January 11<sup>th</sup>)</li>

        <li>The offers received will be ranked according to the selection
        criterias published with the tender, and the ranked list will be
        presented to the board, who makes the decision on which company/-ies
        to outsource to</li>

        <li>The decision will be made public at latest 48 days after the
        deadline for the offers. Given that the offer deadline is January
        11<sup>th</sup>, the decision will be made public no later than
        February 28<sup>th</sup></li>

        <li>The deadline for [å overklage] the decision is YY days after the
        decision has been made public</li>

        <li>The expiration date for the offers is 6 months after the deadline
        for the public tender</li>
      </ol>

      <p>øalsdkfj</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Public Tender Documents</title>

      <p>asdf</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>