<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing — selection criterias</title>

    <subtitle>A precise description of the criterias used for selecting
    vendors</subtitle>

    <version major="1" minor="0">Final version</version>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjurnm@mac.com" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This document is written in conformance with the guidelines from the
      Norwegian ministry of trade and industry (Nærings- og
      handelsdepartementet, NHD) (see «Veileder», see link on the overview
      page).</p>

      <p>The purpose of the selection criterias is to select the economically
      most appealling offer. The main criterion is price, but also indirect
      costs and longer term costs will influence the decision.</p>

      <p>The selection criterias as well as the weighting are decided upon by
      the project board.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selection criterias</title>

      <p>The following criterias will be used in selecting the vendor(s) for
      contract work:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Price</li>

        <li>Technical compatibility with our existing linguistic resources and
        language technology. The less compatible, the more work even for the
        project team, and thus higher indirect costs</li>

        <li>Economical stability of the companies

        <note>This is more like a
        risk analysis thing - does it belong here?</note></li>

        <li>The outlook for future, long-term cooperation with the companies
        (includes willingness to license tools to compile the binary lexicon
        for the proofing tools to Sámediggi and the project group, such that
        linguistic, non-technical updates can be delivered to end users
        without involment from the cooperating companies). This criterion
        involves costs in the longer run, and adds to the overall picture and
        maintenance costs for the proofing tools.</li>

        <li>The future, long term relationship between the participating
        companies and the companies developing the software the proofing tools
        should be integrated with.

        <note>This is also more of a risk analysis
        type - it has no direct economical impact, but the risk is that the
        cooperation between company X and e.g. Microsoft is stopped, blocking
        company X from providing technical updates in the future.</note></li>

        <li>Quality and user evaluation of corresponding tools for other
        languages. In the case of the InDesign hyphenator, it is essential
        that a company can provide a documented capability to develop
        high-quality hyphenation modules, benefitting from our linguistic work
        and tools. In the case of proofing tools for MS Office, it is
        important that the estimated quality of the end user products are high
        enough for our end users, to reduce the risk of extra work and higher
        costs later on in the project.

        <note>Again, this might belong somewhere
        else, but at the same time, this point should have an impact on which
        company to select.</note></li>

        <li>Ability to provide the spellers with corrections and additional
        suggestions tailored to spelling errors typical for (modestly)
        dyslectic writers.

        <note>This criterion is motivated by the fact that
        most of the adult Sámi population has never learned to write their own
        language, and have great difficulties spelling it correctly. It is an
        explicit goal of the project to create spellers that will help this
        group, and if a provider does not have a framework for correcting and
        making suggestions for such spelling errors, much more work will have
        to be put into finding and studying these errors, and adding manual
        entries for correcting such errors. This will lead to higher costs,
        both for the chosen company and for the project team at
        Sámediggi.</note></li>
      </ol>

      <p>The exact documentation needed to support a decision based on these
      criterias is specified in the main public tender document.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Weighting of the criterias</title>

      <p>The above criterias are given a certain weight according to the
      following list (in the same order):</p>

      <ol>
        <li>30 %</li>

        <li>20 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>
      </ol>

      <p>For each criteria, the companies are ranked as winners and loosers -
      winners normally get the full score, while loosers get nothing unless
      otherwise stated -
      within the following limits:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>prize differences within 2% will be regarded as equal, and all within
        that limit will be regarded as winners</li>
        <li>technical compaatibility will be scaled as follows:
          <ul>
            <li>can use our lexicon (with trivial adjustments): 5%</li>
            <li>can use our two-level rules (with trivial adjustments): 10%</li>
            <li>can use our morphological description (with trivial adjustments):
            5 %</li>
          </ul>
          Each company will receive a total precentage corresponding to the sum of
          the above sub-criterias.
        </li>
        <li>The most stable company according to the <a
href="http://odin.dep.no/nhd/norsk/dok/andre_dok/veiledninger/024081-120019/hov004-nn.html"
        >NHD risk analysis model</a> and requested documentation (see
        the main public tender document) is the winner</li>
        <li>Proposal for long-term cooperation:
          <ul>
            <li>lowest cost: 5 %</li>
            <li>most useful toolset and best license conditions: 5 %</li>
          </ul>
        Each company is a winner or looser in each sub-criterion. 5 % variation
        is allowed for the cost, similar to the 2 % above for prize. If two or more
        companies are deemed equal, they all get full points.
        </li>
        <li>The company with the best documented, past and future long-term
        relationship with Microsoft is the winner.</li>
        <li>In the absence of established standards for user evaluation of proofing
        tools, the company with the best published or otherwise documented user
        feedback on their tools is the winner</li>
        <li>The company with the best published or otherwise documented algorithms for
        suggestion mechanisms for dyslectic or otherwise weak writers is the winner.</li>
      </ol>
      
      <p>The winning company is the one with the highest total score, that is, the
      sum of the score for each criterion.</p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The final word</title>

      <p>If two or more companies get identical scores, the final decision is made
      by the project board on the basis of a total evaluation of each remaining
      offer.</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>