<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing — selection criterias</title>

    <subtitle>A precise description of the criteria used for selecting
    vendors</subtitle>

    <version major="2" minor="0">Revised version after the board
    meeting</version>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This document is written in conformance with the guidelines from the
      Norwegian ministry of trade and industry (Nærings- og
      handelsdepartementet, NHD) (see «Veileder», link on the overview
      page).</p>

      <p>The purpose of the selection criteria is to select the economically
      most appealling offer. The main criterion is price, but also indirect
      costs and longer term costs will influence the decision.</p>

      <p>The selection criteria as well as the weighting have been approved by
      the project board.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selection criteria</title>

      <p>The selected offer is the economically most attractive one. That
      implies an evaluation of price and the following criteria:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Technical compatibility with our existing linguistic resources and
        language technology.</li>

        <li>The outlook for future, long-term cooperation with the companies
        (includes willingness to license tools to compile the binary lexicon
        for the proofing tools to Sámediggi and the project group, such that
        linguistic, non-technical updates can be delivered to end users
        without involment from the cooperating companies).</li>

        <li>Quality and user evaluation of corresponding tools for other
        languages. In the case of the InDesign hyphenator, it is essential
        that a company can provide a documented capability to develop
        high-quality hyphenation modules, benefitting from our linguistic work
        and tools. In the case of proofing tools for MS Office, it is
        important that the estimated quality of the end user products are high
        enough for our end users, to reduce the risk of extra work and higher
        costs later on in the project.</li>

        <li>Ability to provide the spellers with corrections and additional
        suggestions tailored to spelling errors typical for (modestly)
        dyslectic writers.</li>

        <li>The long term stability of the companies. <ul>
            <li>The economic stability of the companies</li>

            <li>The future, long term relationship between the participating
            companies and the companies developing the software the proofing
            tools should be integrated with (e.g. Adobe, Microsoft).</li>
          </ul></li>
      </ol>

      <p>The exact documentation needed to support a decision based on these
      criteria is specified in the main public tender document.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Weighting of the criteria</title>

      <p>To guide the total evaluation of the incomming offers, the quality
      criteria are weighted as follows (where optimal fulfilment gives full
      point score):</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Technical compatibility: 0-20 points</li>

        <li>Future cooperation: 0-10 point</li>

        <li>Quality and user satisfaction: 0-10 points</li>

        <li>Dysclectic suggestions: 0-10 points</li>

        <li>Long term stability: 0-10 points</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The final word</title>

      <p>The winning company is the one that, after a total evaluation of
      price and quality criteria, gives the best offer. The decision is made
      by the project board.</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>