<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing — selection criterias</title>

    <subtitle>A precise description of the criterias used for selecting
    vendors</subtitle>

    <version>0.1</version>

    <type>Internal draft</type>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjurnm@mac.com" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This document is written in conformance with the guidelines from the
      Norwegian ministry of trade and industry (Nærings- og
      handelsdepartementet, NHD) (see «Veileder», see link on the overview
      page).</p>

      <p>The purpose of the selection criterias is to select the economically
      most appealling offer. The main criterion is price, but also indirect
      costs and longer term costs will influence the decision.</p>

      <p>The selection criterias as well as the weighting are decided upon by
      the project board.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selection criterias</title>

      <p>The following criterias will be used in selecting the vendor(s) for
      contract work:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>price</li>

        <li>technical compatibility with our existing linguistic resources and
        language technology. The less compatible, the more work even for the
        project team, and thus higher indirect costs</li>

        <li>economical stability of the companies<note>This is more like a
        risk analysis thing - does it belong here?</note></li>

        <li>the outlook for future, long-term cooperation with the companies
        (includes willingness to license tools to compile the binary lexicon
        for the proofing tools to Sámediggi and the project group, such that
        linguistic, non-technical updates can be delivered to end users
        without involment from the cooperating companies). This criterion
        involves costs in the longer run, and adds to the overall picture and
        maintenance costs for the proofing tools.</li>

        <li>the future, long term relationship between the participating
        companies and the companies developing the software the proofing tools
        should be integrated with.<note>This is also more of a risk analysis
        type - it has no direct economical impact, but the risk is that the
        cooperation between company X and e.g. Microsoft is stopped, blocking
        company X from providing technical updates in the future.</note></li>

        <li>Quality and user evaluation of corresponding tools for other
        languages. In the case of the InDesign hyphenator, it is essential
        that a company can provide a substantially higher cost/benefit ratio
        than taking on the task ourselves, as well as a documented capability
        to develop high-quality hyphenation modules. In the case of proofing
        tools for MS Office, it is important that the estimated quality of the
        end user products are high enough for our end users, to reduce the
        risk of extra work and higher costs later on in the
        project.<note>Again, this might belong somewhere else, but at the same
        time, these two points should have an impact on which company to
        select.</note></li>
      </ol>

      <p>The exact documentation needed to support a decision based on these
      criterias is specified in the main public tender document.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Weighting of the criterias</title>

      <p>The above criterias are given a certain weight according to the
      following list (in the same order):</p>

      <ol>
        <li>30 %</li>

        <li>20 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>

        <li>15 %</li>

        <li>10 %</li>

        <li>15 %</li>
      </ol>

      <p>For each criteria, the companies are ranked from 10 (best) to 1,
      based on the documentation given in the offer. The ranking is a simple
      ordering, and does not express any evaluation beyond being equal to,
      better than or worse than the other companies attending. [More...]</p>

      <fixme author="Sjur">I need help with this one - I'm not very good at
      such weighting.</fixme>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The final word</title>

      <p>The final decision regarding which vendor(s) to employ for the
      outsourced tasks is made by the project board.</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>