<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Outsourcing</title>

    <subtitle>Technical specification for project tasks to be
    outsourced</subtitle>

    <version>0.1</version>

    <type>Internal draft</type>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjurnm@mac.com" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>

    <abstract>Integration of proofing tools with commercial applications like
    Adobe InDesign and Microsoft Office is very time consuming and errouneous
    without experience and former practice. It has thus been decided as the
    most cost-effective solution to outsource these tasks. — This document
    describes exactly what is being outsourced, and the technical
    specifications for the deliverables. It also specifies exactly how the
    offer should be divided into independent components, and variants
    thereof.</abstract>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Outsourced tasks</title>

      <p>The outsourced tasks can be summarized in the following table
      (throughout the document, the languages are specified using ISO 639-2
      codes: sme = North Sámi, smj = Lule Sámi).</p>

      <table>
        <caption>Overview of outsourced items</caption>

        <tr>
          <th>Host Application</th>

          <th>Deliverable</th>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>Adobe InDesign 2 and newer</td>

          <td><ul>
              <li>hyphenator (sme)</li>
            </ul></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>Microsoft Office 2000 and newer (running on Windows 2000 and
          newer)</td>

          <td><ul>
              <li>speller (sme, smj)</li>

              <li>hyphenator (sme)</li>
            </ul></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>Microsoft Office 2004 and newer (running on MacOS X 10.3 and
          newer)</td>

          <td><ul>
              <li>speller (sme, smj)</li>

              <li>hyphenator (sme)</li>
            </ul></td>
        </tr>
      </table>

      <note>Should we also include OpenOffice.org in the table? That is, are
      we sure we can make it ourselves if we don't include it? One argument
      pro <em>not</em> including it, would be that we have at least one tool
      set over which we have complete control (barring the Xerox tools, that
      is). The second question is: should we also include a hyphenator for the
      OOo version?</note>

      <section>
        <title>Adobe InDesign</title>

        <p>The Divvun project will outsource the integration of a sme
        hyphenator, and possibly the whole making of the hyphenator. In the
        latter case, the Divvun project will provide the language-specific
        algorithm, and of course be responsible for testing the linguistic
        correctness of the deliverable.</p>

        <note>We need to contact the most important users, and check which
        version they are using or will be using. There's no use in requiring
        the contractor to test against an older version than needed, it will
        only add costs to the project.</note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Microsoft Office</title>

        <p>The Divvun project will outsource the making and the integration of
        the proofing tools for MS Office, based on the computational
        linguistic models developed by the project.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Technical specification of deliverables</title>

      <p>asdf</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>